China Subject Files, Inclusive: 1937-2018, undated, Bulk: 1961-1992
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
China Subject Files
Inclusive: 1937-2018, undated, Bulk: 1961-1992
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
21
Keston Institute, 1969 -
26 A4 document boxes
The China Subject Files contain a variety of materials on multiple topics, including the general progression of China’s political, economic, and social development and the role religion played throughout modern Chinese history.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston collected documents dating from 1937 to 2018 regarding the religious, social, political, and economic changes in China.
Republic of China, 1912-1949
China entered a period of industrialization and modernization in 1912 with the overthrow of the Qing Dynasty during the Xinhai Revolution. The leader of this revolution, Sun Yat-sen, formed the Kuomintang Party, also known as the Nationalist Party of China. After he died in 1925, his protegee Chiang Kai-shek took control of the Kuomintang and worked to consolidate his power within the party and throughout the country. During the late 1920’s, Chiang Kai-shek fought various warlords to win control of the entirety of China. Additionally, he ruthlessly removed and persecuted those who were peaceful but possessed different political ideologies than the Kuomintang Party.
One of these persecuted groups, the Chinese Communist Party, was suppressed in 1927 during a violent incident known as the Shanghai Massacre. Communist members who survived began a series of revolts which instigated the Chinese Civil War. The Chinese National Army of the Kuomintang Party successfully put down these uprisings, and the surviving Communists fled for the mountains in the rural provinces, hoping to find peasant support. Remnants of the Communist army scattered throughout China, disconnected from one another and forced to survive in harsh conditions but still hopeful for victory in limited engagements with the National Army. To evade Chiang Kai-shek’s army, the largest remnant of the Communist Red Army, led by Mao Zedong, left Southern China near Hunan Province to join the Second and Fourth Red Army divisions in Northern China. Mao’s army marched nearly 5,550 miles in 370 days over treacherous mountain terrain to consolidate with other Red Army fragments. Over half of Mao’s army died on the march, but their sheer determination cemented the “Long March” as a major event and led to the rise of Mao Zedong as the leader of the party.
In 1937, the Communist Red Army and the Kuomintang government joined together. The Japanese invasion of China forced these two warring Chinese forces to unite and defend their homeland. This brief reconciliation lasted until Japan’s defeat. In 1946, the Red Army resumed war against Chiang Kai-shek and the Kuomintang, and this time the Communists prevailed. Chiang Kai-shek and his supporters were forced to flee to Taiwan in 1949 and Mao marched into Beijing victoriously. The next decade was filled with drastic new political and religious implementations from Mao and the Communist Politburo.
Religious Life, 1951-
The Religious Affairs Bureau (RAB) was the first great attempt by the Communist government to control spiritual aspects of Chinese life. Established in 1951, RAB was the overarching state oversight for the five officially recognized religions in China: Islam, Taoism (Daoism), Buddhism, Protestantism, and Catholicism. The latter two were the largest religious groups and enjoyed far reaching international support, including from sympathetic Christians and the Vatican. Fearing foreign intervention and manipulation through Western imported religions, RAB required church meetings to be state approved and led by RAB ordained priests and bishops. For this purpose, RAB established the Three-Self Church (Protestant), the Three-Self Patriotic Church (Catholic), and the Islamic Association of China.
The motto of the Three Self-Patriotic Church, often stylized as TSPM, was “self-governance, self-support, self-propagation.” This motto emphasized that the Chinese Church was for Chinese and did not need Western financial or ideological support. TSPM was patterned after the Anglican Church, and many of its leading bishops had been ordained as Anglican priests before the Communist takeover in 1949. One such bishop, K.H. Ting, became the leader of TSPM. While never directly linked with the Communist regime, he publicly stated that socialism and religion were meant to co-exist. The Three Self-Patriotic Church enjoyed considerable success throughout the 1950’s, and even established a new seminary, Nanjing Jinling Theological Seminary to meet the demand for more pastors and bishops. TSPM would effectively be shut down during the Cultural Revolution in the 1970’s, which led to the rise of the underground house church. However, after Mao’s death, the Religious Affairs Bureau and Three Self-Patriotic Church, along with a new Bible printing organization, the Amity Foundation, were reestablished and still exist in 2019.
RAB had a more challenging task pacifying the Chinese Catholic population and transforming it into the government sanctioned Chinese Patriotic Catholic Church. While the Protestant church relied on the prestige and financial aid of foreign entities, which could easily be substituted for Chinese money and recognition, allegiance to the Pope was a fundamental part of Catholicism. RAB had a difficult time creating an alternative figure worthy of such allegiance. Chinese Catholics who refused to denounce the Pope’s authority were not permitted to join the Chinese Patriotic Catholic Church. Priests who communicated with the Vatican were viciously persecuted and imprisoned, where many languished for decades. The underground Chinese Catholic Church flourished with members who refused to denounce the Pope. This underground church was in part led by Ignatius Pin-Mei, who was ordained before the Communist takeover. He spent almost 30 years in prison for his refusal to join the Chinese Patriotic Catholic Church. In 1979, Pope John Paul II secretly made Pin-Mei a Cardinal in recognition of his extreme sacrifice and leadership under extraordinary circumstances.
The Islamic Association of China was established in 1953, though it was considered less important than the official Protestant and Catholic Churches, partly because most Muslims were not Han Chinese but ethnic Uyghurs and Kazakhs. These nomadic herdsmen lived on the Sino-Soviet border and were viewed with suspicion. The Chinese therefore often associated Islam with an inherently subversive “backwater” element. The Islamic Association of China lacked the funding of other officially recognized religious groups and was generally viewed as a means to keep the border population pacified.
Social and Economic Change
In addition to religious structure, the late 1950s brought great social and economic change to China. The Hundred Flowers Campaign and the Great Leap Forward were two examples of drastic Communist Party policies. In 1956, as the Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev relaxed Stalinist policies, Mao initiated the “Hundred Flowers Campaign” which allowed Chinese intellectuals to offer limited criticism of the Chinese Communist Party. The term a “Hundred Flowers Campaign” came from a speech made by Mao, "The policy of letting a hundred flowers bloom and a hundred schools of thought contend is designed to promote the flourishing of the arts and the progress of science.” Although many intellectuals feared retribution, many denounced Communist social and economic practices. Mao allowed the criticism for a year, but in late 1957 aggressively persecuted all who had spoken out as subversive “Rightists.” Many leading scientists, professors, and businessmen were thrown into prison.
In 1958, Mao began a campaign to rapidly industrialize and collectivize China. Food produced on collective farms was confiscated by the government and sold or used to support industrialized endeavors. A resulting famine ensued, and millions starved. While the government hid the disastrous effects of The Great Leap Forward from foreign entities, the Party Congress felt the unhappiness of such polices.
The Cultural Revolution
Mao sensed that he had overstepped and initiated the Cultural Revolution in 1966 to restore his image and power base. His wife Jiang Qing, a former opera singer and actress, orchestrated the Cultural Revolution at the urging of her husband. When the Communists came to power in 1949, he appointed her to a leadership role in the Ministry of Culture. There she effectively suppressed media critical of Mao. After the failure of the Great Leap Forward, Mao decided that Chinese culture needed reform. He appointed Jiang to the Central Cultural Revolution Group and placed her in the powerful Politburo. There she and three other members, collectively known as the Gang of Four, initiated a wave of repression against citizens deemed not revolutionary enough. She created the “Criticize Lin Campaign” and “Criticize Confucius Campaign.” The initial campaign was directed at Lin Biao, Mao’s second in command who died under mysterious circumstances in 1971 in a plane crash as he attempted to flee after a supposed coup. The “Criticize Confucius Campaign” stemmed from an attempt by the Gang of Four to discredit those who read Confucius, which were most of the Chinese leaders and Mao’s direct rivals.
The Red Guards played an ominous role in advancing the Cultural Revolution. In the late 1960’s, Mao encouraged students to form paramilitary groups dedicated to him and the return to revolutionary principles. The Red Guards grew rapidly and essentially became a means to perpetuate the cult of Mao. Their revolutionary enthusiasm led them to quit their jobs, dedicate themselves to reading Mao’s teachings, and denouncing all who were deemed counter-revolutionary. The movement grew out of control. Red Guards roamed the streets destroying property and beating citizens who did not subjugate themselves to their whims. Mao realized the movement had metamorphized into something no longer convenient to his political image and sent the Peoples Liberation Army to suppress Red Guard factions. By 1970, millions of youth who had been part of the Red Guards were sent to work on collective farms as part of reeducation. Those who did not immediately succumb to the harsh elements were often permanently exiled to these farms.
Leadership Transitions
Mao Zedong died in 1976 although he had only been figurehead during his last year. The Gang of Four led by his wife Jiang handled day-to-day affairs. However, without Mao’s protection, Jiang and her co-conspirators were arrested. Hua Guofeng, Mao’s protegee and the new Communist Party Chairman, issued the arrest warrant. Hua served in this role for a short time before he was succeeded by Hu Yaobang. An energetic reformer who had been purged during the Cultural Revolution, he was supported by Deng (Teng) Xiaoping. Although Deng never held high Communist Party leadership positions such as Chairman or General Secretary, from 1978 to his death in 1997, Deng served as the shadow leader. A brilliant reformer, economist, and party member since the beginning, Deng attempted to introduce economic reforms in the early 1960s to fix the problems caused by the Great Leap Forward. Mao condemned his advanced thinking purged him from the party. Deng was rehabilitated in the mid 1960’s but again purged during the Cultural Revolution. Once in power, he opened China to foreign enterprises and investment and nearly single-handedly raised the standard of living. He believed socialism could co-exist with free enterprise and a capitalist market system. Under his leadership and reforms, China grew into an economic superpower.
Deng’s reforms did not come without backlash and social unrest. The Communist Party was long rife with corruption, and many citizens were tired of a double standard and the numerous and often contradictory campaigns against bourgeois sentiments. In April 1989, Hu Yaobang died suddenly from a heart attack. Many viewed him as a reformer who eased censorship and put China on the road toward a more democratic system. Students gathered in Tiananmen Square for Hu’s funeral. They began to chant, asking Premier Li Peng to speak and promise to continue Hu’s reforms. Shortly thereafter, thousands of students and older citizens alike marched on Tiananmen Square officially protesting. The students remained in Tiananmen Square for the next month, and protests spread to other cities in China. In late May, the government declared martial law, and soldiers from the People’s Liberation Army marched on Tiananmen Square. In early June, tanks rolled into the Square. In the aftermath, hundreds of students died, though official reports say that no one was killed. Chinese citizens, and the rest of the world, watched stunned as the events unfolded. However, the soldiers succeed in squelching the protests and hope for democracy for China died with those students.
Scope and Content
China Subject Files consist of newspaper clippings, typescripts, background reports, handwritten letters, broadcasts, and bibliographic references.
The materials range from 1937-2018. The collection pertains primarily to the general progression of China’s political, economic, and social development. The files focus on the rise of the Communist Party and the power struggle within the party. Additionally, the effects of various economic campaigns, such as The Great Leap Forward and cultural campaigns, such as the Cultural Revolution, are reviewed. China maintained relationships with various foreign governments, and the files reflect China’s growing influence in spheres such as Africa and South America. China’s relationship with Western powers was tumultuous at times, stemming from the West’s objections to the Chinese human rights abuse and political suppression. This collection also reviews the role religion played throughout modern Chinese history. Both the suppression and revival of religious affairs under the Communist Party is included.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received a portion of the Chinese materials in folders organized by categories and a larger portion in no particular order. The materials have been organized by specific categories and denominations and subsequently arranged thematically and chronologically.
Currently, the China Subject Files are arranged in two series: I. General and II. Denominational materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 21.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Bstan-)`dzin-rgya-mtsho, Dalai Lama XIV, 1935-; Cheng, Nien, 1915-2009.; Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975.; Chos-kyi-dbaṅ-phyug, Panchen Lama VII, 1938-1989.; Deng, Xiaoping, 1904-1997.; Fang, Lizhi.; Jiang, Qisheng, 1948-; Lin, Biao, 1908-1971.; Liu, Shaoqi, 1898-1969.; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976.; Qiao, Guanhua, 1913-1983.; Wang, Dan, 1969-; Wang, Juntao.; Wu, Hongda Harry.; Zhao, Ziyang.; Zhou, Enlai, 1898-1976.; Zhu, De, 1886-1976.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- China.
Places
China -- Emigration and immigration.; China -- Foreign relations -- 1949-1976.; China -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union.; China -- History -- Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976.; China -- History -- Tiananmen Square Incident, 1989.; China -- Religion.; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- China.; Tibet Autonomous Region (China) -- Politics and government.; Tibet Autonomous Region (China) -- Relations -- China.; United States -- Foreign relations -- China.
Subjects
Buddhism -- China -- History.; Christian martyrs -- China.; Christianity -- China.; Church and state -- China.; Civil rights -- China.; Concentration camps -- China.; Confucianism.; Forced labor -- China.; Freedom of religion -- China -- History -- 20th century.; Gang of Four Trial, Beijing, China, 1980-1981.; Human rights -- China.; Minorities -- China.; Missionaries -- China -- History.; Missions -- China.; Philosophy, Confucian.; Political prisoners -- China.; Protestant churches -- Missions -- China -- History.; Religion and state -- China.; Tibetans -- Ethnic identity.
Genres
Bibliographies.; Book reviews.; Broadcasts.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Records (Documents); Typescripts.
- General, 1937-2018, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  The General series contains materials related to the general history of China; Chinese leaders and legacies; international relations; post cultural revolution changes, both social and economic; family, education, and youth; communism and the Communist Party of China; political dissidents; law, courts, and prisons; human rights violations; religious persecution; house churches; social unrest and Chinese response; economics; everyday life; and media, arts, and literature.
  - History. General (1 of 13), 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History. General (2 of 13), 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History. General (3 of 13), 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - History. General (4 of 13), 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - History. General (5 of 13), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - History. General (6 of 13), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History. General (7 of 13), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History. General (8 of 13), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History. General (9 of 13), 1989 January-July (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History. General (10 of 13), 1989 August-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History. General (11 of 13), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - History. General (12 of 13), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History. General (13 of 13), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Deng (1 of 2), 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Deng (2 of 2), 1979-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Deng's Death and Legacy, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Hu Yaobang, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Hua Kuo-Feng, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Life of Mao, 1962- 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Death of Mao, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Legacy of Mao, 1976- 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Lin Biao, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Chiang Kai-Shek, 1982, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Madame Soong, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Zhao Ziyang, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Chu Teh, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Liu Shaochi, 1960-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Nien Cheng, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Chiao Kuan-Hua, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Chou En-Lai, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Chinese Leaders and Legacies. Deaths and Obituaries of Political Leaders, 1966-1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (1 of 18), 1960-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (2 of 18), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (3 of 18), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (4 of 18), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (5 of 18), 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (6 of 18), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (7 of 18), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (8 of 18), 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (9 of 18), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (10 of 18), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (11 of 18), 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (12 of 18), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (13 of 18), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (14 of 18), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (15 of 18), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (16 of 18), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (17 of 18), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China (18 of 18), 1992-2002, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China. Prepared Reports on Tibet, 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China. Cultural Revolution in Tibet, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - International Relations. Tibet and China. Arrests of Tibetans, 1986-1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - National Minorities in China, 1973-1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Elections in China, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - People's Liberation Army, 1976-1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Espionage, 1966-1985 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Emigration, Immigration, and Defections, 1970-1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - International Relations. Sino - Soviet Relations, 1962-1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - International Relations. Chinese Views on African-Americans, 1968-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - International Relations. Western Investments in China, 1977-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - International Relations. China in Latin America, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - International Relation. Sino -Canadian Relations, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - International Relations. Sino-Cuban Relations, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - International Relations. American Diplomatic Missions to China, 1974-1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - International Relations. Sino-US Relations, 1974-2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - International Relations. Sino-Soviet Relations (1 of 2), 1981-1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - International Relations. Sino-Soviet Relations (2 of 2), 1978-1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - International Relations. Sino-Croatian Relations, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - International Relations. China-UN Relations, 1964-1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)